# 你看 兄弟家的牛
Look! My buddy’s cattle.
# 那麼多 要發財啦
So many! It’s a great fortune!
# 過去看一下
Let’s go and have a look.
# 哇 好多小牛哇 好小的
Wa! A lot of calves, really small ones
# 這條肚子那麼大
Why does this one have such a big belly?
# 你看 這小牛很聽話的哦
Look! This calf is really nice, you know.
# 來 摸一下
C’mon! Let me touch you!
# 它不肯
It doesn’t want it.
# 不肯讓我摸
It doesn’t want my touch.
# 那麼 牛頭哦 那條
That one, the Alpha, that one.
# 那條是 看到沒有 就那條 那條就是公牛
That one is… See? The one right over there, that one is a bull,
# 最大的一條
the biggest one.
# 全部都是它老婆
These are all its wives.
# 這小的 好可愛這小的哦
This small one, this small one is really cute, you know.
# 兄弟又在下面那一點 不然抱一條就可以走啦
My buddy is down there. Otherwise, I can simply take one and run away.
# 好小啊 應該一百斤都不到
It’s so small. I think it’s not even fifty kilograms.
# 那條 那條牛在那裡抓癢癢
That one, that one is scratching its itchy skin.
# 誒 一說它它就不抓啦
Ey? It stops once I mention it.
# 一起抓
C'mon! Scratch together!
# 這條怎麼那麼像我的呢
Why does this one look like me so much?
# 你看 這條 這條就是公牛來的 最大條
Look! This one, this one is a bull. It’s the biggest.
# 哇 這肯定最少能賣一萬多塊錢
Wa! I am sure that it is worth at least ten thousand RMB.
# 一身都是肉
It’s so meaty.
# 那脖子上這一坨 全是瘦肉來的 這一坨 供起來的
That part on the neck, is all lean meat. That part, the wedging part
# 過來
Come here!
# 這條小牛還在吃奶
The calf is still having milk.
# 好不好吃
Does it taste good?
# 過來
Come here!
# 給你吃
It’s for you.
# 要不要
You want it?
# 它不要
No, it doesn’t.
# 它們都吃飽啦 吃的肚子好大
They’ve all eaten a lot. Their bellies are all that big now.
# 等下我去抓隻羊回來
Let me catch a goat in a while.
# 這個牛就 摸都摸不到 抓不到的
The cattle, well, I can’t even touch them, let alone catching them.
# 去抓兄弟家的羊
Let me catch my buddy’s goat.
# 你看 今年的野果
Look! The wild fruits this year,
# 好多哦
are plentiful!
# 這個是野杮子
These are wild persimmons.
# 這產量太高啦 可能長得比較瘦
The yield is too high. So they might be a bit skinny,
# 像個橄欖果一樣
just like olives.
# 營養 供給不足
They don’t have, enough nutrition.
# 兩邊都有哇 這兩棵樹雙胞胎
They’re growing on both sides. These two trees are twin.
# 這都壞了一些 一些都壞掉啦
Some are rotten, some are rotten here.
# 黑啦
They’re black.
# 你看 這個
Look! This is,
# 這個是那個
this is, well...
# 叫甚麼
How is it called?
# 就是牛哇 羊很喜歡吃葉子的這個
It’s like, the cattle, the goats like its leaves a lot.
# 豬仔也特別喜歡吃它的葉子
The piggies also like its leaves.
# 但我就不知道它叫甚麼
But I have no ideas how it is called.
# 嗯 長的
Um. It’s sort of like,
# 像一條毛毛蟲一樣 那麼大條
just like a caterpillar. So big
# 太大啦 羊吃不到 吃得到的話葉子全部都被它們吃光啦
It’s too big. The goats can’t eat it. Otherwise, all leaves would have been eaten.
# 這個不知道是花 還是果
Well, I don’t know whether they’re flowers, or fruits.
# 這個小辣條 小辣條一樣
It’s like “latiao” (lit: spicy stripes, local snacks), just like “latiao”.
# 這個我們這邊叫香藤子 它的藤子是香的
Look! It is called “xiang tengzi” (lit: fragrant branches, valeria) here. Its branches have a fragrant scent.
# 它叫香藤子
So it’s called “xiang tengzi”.
# 你看 這種都可以吃啦 這種
Look! These are edible, these fruits.
# 是啊 只是不是很熟而已
Yup! They’re just not really that ripe.
# 但是不影響它的口感
But the texture is not affected.
# 你看 這個果肉 你看
Look! The pulp… Look!
# 哦 全部都熟啦
Oh! They're all ripe.
# 先下手為強
The first-mover gains the advantage.
# 等下兄弟過來啦 全部把它摘光
My buddy's gonna pick everything when he comes in a while.
# 嗯 紅的 看到沒有 這種
Um! It’s red. See? This one
# 很好吃的哦
It’s really tasty, you know.
# 今年夠多 今年一樹都是
There are a lot this year. They’re all over the tree.
# 這籽不能吃的這籽 要把它吐出來喲
The seeds are not edible. You gotta spit them out.
# 現在還不是很熟
They are not really that ripe at this moment.
# 再過一個禮拜左右就過來 就可以摘啦
Come again in a week. We can pick by then.
# 一個禮拜就整個都是紅的啦
They'll become all red in a week.
# 我現在摘的時候都挑一點這個
Now I pick only those, I mean,
# 紅的就摘 不紅的我都不摘
only the red ones, but not the green ones.
# 搞幾個
Let me pick some.
# 搞幾個回去就好啦
Just a few back home would be enough.
# 這還不是很熟
They are still not that ripe.
# 把那個紅一點的把它摘掉就好啦
I just pick those which are red,
# 不怎麼紅的就放在這裡 讓它更紅更好吃
and leave the greener ones here. Let them become tastier when they become red.
# 不了雨 現在車都上不來啦
It has rained. The car can’t go up here.
# 這有黃泥在這裡 不然一下子就可以上的去啦
Here’s mud on the path. Otherwise the car can go all the way up.
# 上次我們都是一路直上
That’s what we did last time.
# 我們走路進去啦
We gottta walk.
# 上面一個很紅的那個香藤子哦
There’s a very red “xiang tengzi” up there.
# 直接把這個竹子砍掉
I need to chop down this bamboo right away,
# 才能 拿得到 要不拿不到的
so that, I can take it. Otherwise I can’t take it.
# 這根竹子 它本來就死的
This bamboo, it’s already dead actually.
# 我把它砍下來而已
I just chop it down.
# 我把這個藤子要砍掉
These branches need to be chopped away as well.
# 不砍掉的話它下不來
Otherwise they’re not coming down.
# 砍掉之後 它明年長得更茂盛的哦 這個
They’re gonna grow even better next year, after chopping it away, you know.
# 是不是
Am I right?
# 明年長得 明年這裡可以長出新枝出來
Next week, new branches are gonna grow here next year.
# 更好看
It will look even better.
# 你看 哎呀 這棵
Look! Aya. This one
# 漂亮吧 這棵
It’s pretty, isn’t it? This one
# 看一下熟了沒有
Let me see if it is ripe.
# 嗯
Um!
# 沒熟 這個
It's not yet ripe, this one.
# 再嘗一個
Let me try another one.
# 不是很熟
It’s not really that ripe.
# 它慢慢 慢慢就熟啦
It’s getting ripe, slowly, and gradually.
# 下雨天
Cuz it rains,
# 味道沖淡啦
so the flavour is washed away.
# 這個 很甜的
It should be, really sweet.
# 還有一個 剩下的給你啦
Here’s still a little bit. The rest is yours.
# 你看 這裡有一顆
Look! Here's a…
# 我們這邊叫蓮麻拐
It’s called “lian ma gai” (hog plum) here.
# 又大又黃哦 又個蓮麻拐
It’s big and brown, this “lian ma gai”.
# 因為它生在深山裡面
Cuz it’s growing deep in the mountain.
# 所以它 沒人 很少人 很少進 很少人進來這裡
So it’s, nobody, few people, seldom, people seldom come it.
# 嗯
Um~
# 好香啊
It smells so good.
# 你看 現在都下雨啦
Look! It’s raining now.
# 我去他那個 羊棚裡面躲一下雨
Let’s go to his, well, his goat shed and take a shelter here.
# 要不然就被濕身的
Otherwise, we’ll all get soaked.
# 這兄弟做的路哦
This path was built by my buddy.
# 那麼多草
So many weeds.
# 現在只能蹲在這裡啦 這裡才能躲雨
Now I can only stay here. It’s the only shelter.
# 等雨停了 我再回去
When the rain stops, we'll go back,
# 順便牽一條羊
taking a goat with us.
# 鏈條我都帶好啦
I’m even coming with a chain.
# 放在這裡
Let me put it here,
# 這刀也放在這裡
and the knife as well.
# 你看 下好大雨哦 回不去啦
Look! The rain is so heavy. We can’t get back now.
# 我要等雨停哦 雨停啦
We gotta wait until the rain stops. We can’t go back,
# 才能回得去
before the rain stops.
# 這百香果都還沒熟
These passion fruits are all not yet ripe.
# 都是青的
They’re all still green.
# 下吧 下吧
C’mon! Keep raining!
# 下多大我都不要緊
I don’t care at all.
# 上面有羊 下面有雞 這還有百香果
There are goats up there, chickens down there, and also passion fruits here.
# 這裡還有大米喲
Here’s rice as well!
# 大米放在這裡
The rice is here.
# 不走啦 今天晚上 要再下大一點
We not leaving, not leaving tonight, if it rain gets worse.
# 柴火又有 全是現成的
Here’s also firewood. Everything is ready here,
# 而且有新鮮的
and everything is fresh.
# 你看 那個羊 肚子餓啦 兄弟都不來放
Look! That goat, is starving now. My buddy is not taking them out.
# 現在都不午兩三點鐘啦 它還不來放
It’s almost three in the afternoon now, but he’s still not taking them out.
# 餓的它都把頭伸出來
It’s so hungry that it’s peeping out.
# 你看 今天增加了好多小羊啊
Look! Here are a lot of kids this year.
# 看到沒 小羔羊
See? The small kids.
# 搞一條漂亮一點的
Let me get a prettier one,
# 回去
and take it back home.
# 聽說
I’ve heard that,
# 看好多都被閹掉啦
many have already been neutered.
# 過來 過來 過來
Come here, come here, come here!
# 過來
Come here!
# 就這隻
Alright! This one!
# 你看 這個毛好靚啊
Look! Its coat is really beautiful!
# 發亮的毛
Shiny coat
# 去我家啦
Go home with me.
# 給你發老婆
I’ll give you wives.
# 兩個哦
Not one but two!
# 叫他們兩個枱回去
I ask these two guys to carry it back.
# 刀放著
Put the knife here.
# 刀
Knife?
# 是
Yup
# 不用放
No need
# 放下來 放下來
Put it down, put it down
# 放下來是吧
Put it down?
# 嗯
Um
# 喂 狗
Hey! Dog!
# 狗
Dog!
# 這怎麼有一個耳朵
Why is here an ear?
# 小耳朵
A tiny ear
# 咩 去 找你姐姐去
Meh~ Go! Meet your big sisters.
# 走
Go!
# 走 走
Go! Go!
# 上面很好玩的
It’s a lot of fun up there.
# 你有伴在那裡
You'll have your companions there!
# 誒 快點
Ey! Hurry up!
# 不認識嗎
Don’t you know them?
# 咩
Meh~
# 把它放啦 跑它們在一起就好啦
I'm gonna release it. Let them mingle together. It will be fine.
# 嘿 不聽話是不是
Heh! Naughty, aren’t you?
# 我是把它(你)放啦
I’m just trying to release you!
# 好 可以
Good! Alright!
# 快 跟它們在一起
C’mon! Go and join them!
# 兩個人打它
They both beat it!
# 狗
Dog!
# 它現在就熟悉啦 跟這兩條羊
It’s starting to know them, these two goats.
# 兩個你的姐姐哦 這個 跟它們在一起啊
They’re your big sisters. Come and stay with them, alright?
# 它在幹嘛
What is it doing?
# 你看 它們三個人
Look! All three of them.
# 全在一起玩啦
are together now.
# 不用管的 它們慢慢會回來的
Leave them alone. They’ll be coming back in a while.
# 我們商量了一下 把那隻羊給它取一個名字
We’ve agreed, to give that goat a name.
# 它的名字就叫作羊肉包
His name is, Lamb Bun.
# 它在上面 跑啦
He has run away, up there now.
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.
# 我拿點東西來餵一下它
Let me get something to feed him.